Finding Aid for National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. University of Michigan College Chapter records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
National Association for the Advancement of Colored People University of Michigan College Chapter records 1973-1989
National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. University of Michigan College Chapter.
85315 Bimu F24 2
The collection documents the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People: University of Michigan College Chapter from 1973 to 1989. Documents include the student chapter's involvement in NAACP conventions, minority recruitment and retention for the University of Michigan, in improving faculty/staff/leadership relations and other internal and community activities.
1 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Charles F. Holman (Donor no. 6080 ) in August 1977. Further accessions were made in 1982 and 1991
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The principal objective of the NAACP is to ensure the political, educational, social and economic equality of minority group citizens and to achieve equality or rights and eliminate race prejudice among the citizens of the United States. The group relies on the press, petitions, ballots, and courts/legal action. The student chapter at the University of Michigan, officially established on November 11, 1975, focused its efforts on educating its membership and the university community on both national issues, such as opposition to the supreme court nominee Robert Bork in 1987, and local issues, such as voter registration drives and minority student dorm environment satisfaction. Other activities include an ongoing Ann Arbor employment project and various rallies and marches for social justice issues. The collection was donated in three accessions in 1977, 1982 and 1991.
The collection is made up of five series: Administrative Records, Conference and Symposia, Correspondence, Publications, and Reports and Surveys. Items from all three accessions have been re-organized into these series. The order within each file has been maintained.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Students.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; Minority college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
- Administrative Records
  The Administrative Records series consist of board and committee meeting minutes and agendas as well as member lists and some administrative correspondence, reports and planning material. The Miscellaneous Items folder contains newspaper articles, event information, membership committee lists, speaker series information and other task force and correspondence documents.
  - Board of Directors Material 1977, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Bursley Hall Board 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Items 1986-1989 (Box 1)
  - Fund Raising Banquet Proposal (Box 1)
  - General Membership Items -- agendas and minutes 1986-1989 (Box 1)
  - General Reports 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - Membership and Attendance List (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1985-1989 (Box 1)
  - National Board 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Nominating Forms 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - Planning Committee 1985-1986 (Box 1)
- Conferences and Symposia
  The Conference and Symposia series documents the organization, content, literature and outcomes (e.g. resolutions) from various local and regional conferences. Conference topics include a 1977 leadership training conference and a 1978 conference on the Allan Bakke affirmative action court decision.
  - Bakke Symposium, Detroit 1978 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Symposium 1974, 1975, 1981 (Box 1)
  - National Leadership Summit, Chicago 1978 (Box 1)
  - Regional Conferences 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - State and Regional 1975-1979, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series contains letters between the UM chapter's leadership and the University of Michigan community as well as the national NAACP and other outside groups.
  - General Correspondence 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence 1976 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence 1977 (Box 1)
  - National NAACP correspondence 1976 (Box 1)
  - National NAACP correspondence 1977 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Officers 1986-1989 (Box 1)
  - Letters from the President 1986-1989 (Box 1)
  - Letters Received 1986-1989 (Box 1)
- Press and Publications
  The Press and Publications series holds copies of the chapter's pamphlets and publications such as "Street News: The Black Community-Student Newspaper of Ann Arbor" as well as press releases and newspaper articles about the local chapter. Also collected are various local articles on racial issues.
  - Articles 1986-1989 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous printed works 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - Press Releases 1986-1989 (Box 1)
- Task Force Surveys, Drafts and Reports
  The Task Force Surveys, Drafts and Reports series documents the Task Force on Black College Students Report compiled by executive secretary Charles F. Holman between 1976-1978. Included are the questionnaires on which the report is based, various correspondence and notes about the task force, and drafts of the report including the final report titled The Black Experience & U. of M. Residence Halls 1968-1977.
  - Draft Report on Employment of Minority Students in Ann Arbor 1976 (Box 1)
  - Holman Notes, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Holman Notes Detroit NAACP (Box 1)
  - Holman Notes UM (Box 1)
  - Questionnaire on Black Students' Problems, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Questionnaire Bursley Hall Weight Room 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Report on Problem Areas in UM for Minority Students 1977 (Box 1)
  - Report on Residence Halls 1968-1977 (Box 1)